MEHMET FURKAN SAHİN

Cell Phone: +90 539 2026442 E-mail: sahinffurkan@gmail.com GitHub: /furkansahin Personal web-site:mfsh.in

I am a passionate programmer trying to improve myself in different fields. I have work experiences in C, JavaScript and SQL. I have been developing applications with Java for 5 years. The moment I heard my Slovenian friend loves cBioPortal, I realized that I love my job.

EDUCATION

2012-2017 June Bilkent University, Computer Science, Ankara, TURKEY: B.Sc. granted comprehensive scholarship. CGPA: 3.75/4.00 Major CGPA: 3.92/4.00 (CS classes)

2015-Fall École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, Switzerland: Exchange program, Computer Science (IN, B.Sc.)

EXPERIENCE

2016 October, Publication, The cBioPortal for cancer genomics and its application in precision oncology: Author, detailed information can be found in the link.

2016 July - 2016 August, Institute of High Performance Computing, A*Star, Singapore: Research Assistant. Worked on a 3D robotic arm model which can play ping pong.

2016 May - 2016 July, Citus Data, Istanbul: Software Engineering Internship, created percentile approximations extension for PostgreSQL. Percentile queries are speeded up 400x.

2015 August - 2016 January, Human-Computer Interaction Group - EPFL, Switzerland: Undergrad Researcher, developed a data visualization tool for MOOCs data with D3 JavaScript library.

2015 June - 2015 September, Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center, New York, USA: Software engineering intern, developed Java-Script based graph visualization tools for Genomics Data with Cytoscape JS.

SCHOLARSHIPS, AWARDS, HONORS

2012-Present, Bilkent University High Honor Student

2015, TUBITAK (Turkish Science Foundation) Undergraduate Researcher Scholarship

2014-2013, IEEEXtreme 8.0-7.0 Programming Competition: As a team of three undergraduate students, which is named TechWeb, ranked 1st. in Turkey, 30th. In IEEE Region 8, 73rd. in the world among 2500 teams competing throughout the world.

PROJECTS

CrypDist, Senior Project - Present: CrypDist is a blockchain based encrypted content distribution network. The project aims to avoid data access blocks and reduce the time needed to deliver big data. I take responsibilities on the development of distribution system.

Section Checker, Bilkent University - 2016: A program which checks available quotas periodically for desired course section and warns the user in case of availability is developed with a colleague. It was used by Bilkent University students in course selection period.

HDR, Citus Data - 2016: HDR is a Histogram based percentile approximation extension for PostgreSQL database systems. It provides 400x speed increase with 0.0001 error ratio. The whole project is handled by myself.

Beatify, EPFL - 2015: Beatify is created as a group project with 2 more colleagues. It is a music player android app which finds the best music from your Spotify account according to the instant heart rate of the user. I implemented Spotify integration.

cBioPortal - Network transformation, MSKCC - 2015: Network tab of cBioPortal is transformed from a flash based version to Cytoscape JS. The whole project is handled by myself.

COMPUTER SKILLS

Programming: Java, C/C++, SQL(PostgreSQL, MySQL), JavaScript, Scala, Python, Android, D3, Cytoscape JS.

Operating Systems: OS X, Microsoft Windows, Linux

Interests: Distributed Systems, Databases, Algorithms, Big Data, Cloud Architecture, Mobile applications.

Courses: CS 425 - Algorithms for Web-Scale Data, CS 476 - Automata Theory and Formal Languages, CS 342 - Operating Systems, CS 353 Database Systems, CS 315 - Programming Languages, EPFL - Functional Programming, EPFL - Lab on Apps Development for Tablets and Smartphones, EPFL - Projet en Informatique I.

LANGUAGES

Turkish: Native English: Fluent French: Beginner German: Beginner

MEMBERSHIP & PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

2014 - 2015 Young Guru Academy Conference Participant

2013 – 2015 Bilkent IEEE Coordinator – International IEEE Member: Coordinated volunteer students to organize technical and social events and trainings about courses to help other Bilkent students.